欢迎回来, 在这个视频中, 我们要讲一些题外话
Welcome back. In this video, we're going to take a little digression and talk about
正式语言。正式语言在理论计算机中扮演了重要角色
formal languages. A formal language has played a big role in theoretical computer
科学, 但它们在编译器中也很重要因为在编译器内部,
science but they're also very important in compilers because inside of the compiler,
我们通常有几种不同的正式语言, 我们在操纵。
we typically have several different formal languages that we're manipulating. A
正则表达式是正式语言的一个例子但它确实很有帮助
regular expressions are one example of a formal language but it's actually helpful
我认为在理解常规语言和所有的正式语言时我们会看到
I think in understanding regular languages and all the formal languages we'll see
后来在后面的视频中, 我们讨论了一般的正式语言,
later on in later videos to talk about what the formal languages in general, So,
让我们从定义开始, 一个正式的语言有一个字母表, 所以, 一些
let's begin with the definition. A formal language has an alphabet, So, some set of
字母sigma, 然后在字母表上的一种语言就是一组字符串
letter sigma. And then a language over that alphabet is just a set of strings of
从字母表中抽取的字符, 在这种情况下, 或者是常规语言, 我们有
the characters drawn from the alphabet. So in the case or regular languages, we had
有一些方法可以建立一系列的字符但是其他类型的
certain ways of building up sets of strings of characters but other kinds of
语言会有不同的字符串集, 一般来说, 是一种正式的语言
languages would have different sets of strings. And in general, a formal language
它只是一些字母表上的任何一组字符串, 这是一种语言的例子
is just any set of strings over some alphabet. An example of a language that
你们熟悉的是一种来自于英语字母的字母表它是
you're familiar with is a form from the alphabet of English characters and it is
只是一组英语句子, 现在, 这不是一种正式的语言
just the set of English sentences. Now, This is not quite a formal language and
我们可能不同意哪一串英文字符实际上是有效的
that we might disagree in which string of English characters are in fact valid
英语句子但是我们可以想象我们可以定义一些规则
English sentences but one could imagine that we could define some rules that we
会说某些字符串是英语句子而另一些则不是, 如果我们
would say the certain strings are English sentences and others aren't. And if we
可以达成协议这将是一种正式的语言, 现在有很多
could come to this on agreement this would be a fully formal language. Now a much
更严格的正式语言应该是这样的, 我们可以
more rigorous formal language would be something like the following; we could
选择我们的字母表是问字符集, 语言是
pick our alphabet to be the asking character set and the language to be the
所有有效的C程序集, 所以这绝对是一个定义良好的语言。
set of all Valid C program. So this is definitely a very well defined language.
这正是C编译器所接受的输入集。
This is exactly the set of inputs that C compilers will accept. And the, the
我想在这里画出的重要对比是, 字母表其实很有趣。
important contrast I want to draw here is that the alphabet is actually interesting.
所以, 不同的正式语言, 你知道吗？有一个非常非常不同的字母表
So, different formal languages, you know? Have a very, very different alphabets and
我们不能真正讨论什么是正式的语言或者是什么类型的字符串
we can't really talk a bout what the formal language is or what sort of strings
我们感兴趣的是, 除非找到字母表, 另一个重要的概念
we're interested in unless to find that alphabet. Another important concept for
许多正式语言都是一个意义函数, 通常我们有一个
many formal languages is a meaning function. Typically we have one of the
我们的语言中的字符串我们称它为表达式e和表达式
strings in our language and let's call that some expression e and the expression
e本身就是一段语法, 从某种意义上讲, 它是一个程序
e by itself is just a piece of syntax. It's a program in some sense or it
代表了我们的一些东西, 这就是我们实际上的东西
represents something else that we're, Which is the thing we're actually
感兴趣的是, 我们有一个函数L它将语言中的字符串映射到
interested in. And so we have a Function L that maps the strings in the language to
它们的意思, 例如, 在正则表达式的例子中
their meanings. And so for example in the case of the regular expressions, this
它是一个正则表达式, 它会映射到一组字符串。
would be a regular expression. And that would be map to a set of strings. The
常规的语言, 这个正则表达式我们看到了一个例子
regular language that, that regular expression to notes and we saw an example
上次我们写出了正则表达式的会议函数我们来看看
where we wrote out the meeting function for regular expression last time so let's
用正则表达式作为一个例子我要先把它的意思写下来
use regular expressions as an example and I'm gonna first write down the meaning of
正则表达式, 我在上个视频中把它写下来如果你们还记得
the regular expressions. The way I wrote it down in the last video so if you recall
我们有一个正则表达式epsilon这表示一个集合, 它只包含一个
we had a regular expression epsilon and that denoted a set, Which contain just one
字符串, 也就是空字符串, 然后我们有一个正则表达式C
string, namely the empty string. And then we had a regular expression C for every
字母表中的字符也需要一个字符串, 即一个字符串
character in the alphabet which also do need a socketing just one string namely
单个字符c, 然后, 我们有一堆复合表达式, 所以
the single character C. And then, we had a bunch of compound expressions. So for
例如, A+B, 它等于集合A和B的结合我们有
example, A + B. That was equal to the union of the sets A and B and we had the
连接, 我可以, 我可以, 听不清A和B, 这就等于
concatenation so I could, I could [inaudible] A and B and that was equal to
一个叉乘, 我从每个集合中选择一个字符串并连接起来
a cross product where I selected a string from each set in order and concatenated
它们在一起, 最后是迭代, 所以我可以写一个星星
them together. And finally there was iteration so I could write a star and that
是联邦除以I, 大于0的集合A到I, I结束。
was the union over I. Greater than zero of all the sets A to the I, I ends. An
关于这个定义的有趣之处在于你可以看到它们在映射
interesting thing about this definition is you can see that they were mapping, over
我们有表达式, 我换个颜色, 这里是表达式
we have expressions and let me switch colors here, over here we have expressions
这里是集合, 但这里有一些奇怪的东西
and over here we have the sets. But there's something kind of odd about the
这是书面的, 不太对, 因为你们可以清楚地看到, 我们有
way this is written and not quite right cuz you can see here we clearly, we have
一个表达式, 我们有一个语法A+B然后在另一边
an expression. We have a piece of syntax A + B and then somehow on the other side
这个A, 这个A和这个B已经神奇地变成了我们的集合
this, this A, this A and this B have magically turned into sets that we're
把这个和下面的结合在这里我们从这里选择一个元素
taking the union of and similarly down here we're choosing an element from this
集合, 但是这个集合也是一个表达式, 这意味着什么？我们在某种程度上
set but this set is also an expression and what does that mean? Somehow we're
把表达式中的集合合并起来这就是。意思函数是
conflating the sets in the expressions and this is what. The meaning function is
想要解决这个问题, 这是他们, 或者, 或者想要弄清楚的, 所以我们,
intended to fix and this what they, or, or, or intended to make clear. So we, what
我们想说的是有一些映射, 即语言L
we really wanted to say is that there's some mapping, That the language L epsilon
集合是这样的, 所以L从表达式映射到一组字符串, 好的,
is the set so the, so L maps from expressions into sets of strings. Okay,
它是一个将一个映射到另一个的函数你还没见过这个符号
It's a function that maps one to the other and it you haven't seen this notation
之前, 这是描述函数的标准符号, 它表示L
before, this is a standard notation for describing functions. It does says that L
是定义域中的一个函数, 在这个域中的这个范围, 好的。
is a function from things in the domain, in this domain to this range, okay. And
类似地, 这个表达式的语言是集合它变得非常有用
similarly the language of this expression is the set and it becomes really useful
对于复合表达式因为这里我们说的是这个表达式的语言
for the compound expressions cuz here we say the language of this expression. Is
等于a的语言和B的语言现在你们可以看到
equal to the language of a union with the language of B and now you can see the
递归, 首先我们用L来解释A和B我们取它的结合
recursion. First we interpret A and B using L and we take the union of the
结果, 好了, 现在很清楚什么是资产, 什么是表达式
result. Okay, so now it's clear what's asset and what's an expression and
类似地, a和B连接的语言, 我们要
similarly here the language of a concatenated with B, we are going to
从这两个表达式的语言中选择元素然后我们将
select elements from the language of these two expressions and then we're going to
从这两个集合中形成另一个集合, 最后是迭代, a的语言
form another set from those two sets. And finally for iteration, The language of a
恒星等于结合了一堆表达式的意义, A
star is equal to the union over the meaning of a bunch of expressions, A to
I是一个表达式, 这是一段语法我们要把它转换成A
the I is an expression. This is a, a piece of syntax and we have to convert it to A
集合N的顺序来取这个联合, 关于这个, 是。正确的定义
set N order to take the union. And so about this, is. The proper definition of
正则表达式的含义我们已经明确了含义函数L
the meaning of regular expressions where we've made the meaning function L explicit
我们已经展示了如何递归地应用L来分解化合物
and we've shown exactly how recursively we apply L to decompose the compound
表达式到几个表达式中我们计算它的含义
expressions into several expressions that we compute the meaning of and then
从那些独立的小s中计算出这些集合, 还有其他的
computed the sets from those from those separate smaller s ets. So, there's other
使用会议功能的原因, 我们只看到其中一个
reasons for using a meeting function. We just saw one of them which is to make
清楚。在我们的定义中什么是语法, 什么是语义。
clear. What is syntax and what is semantics in our definitions. Some parts
定义是表达, 有些部分是, 意思或集合
of the definition are expression and some parts are the, the meanings or the sets
使用L表明, L的参数是, 程序或
and the using L makes it clear that the arguments to L are the, the programs or
表达式和结果是集合, 输出是集合, 但是
the expressions and the results Are the, the sets. The outputs are the sets, But
分离语法和语义还有一些其他的原因。
there are a couple of other reasons for separating syntax and semantics. One, is
它允许我们把符号看作一个单独的问题, 如果我们有
that it allows us to consider notation as a separate issue. That is if we have
语法和语义是不同的, 我们可以在保持语法和语法的同时改变语法
syntax and semantics being different, then we can vary the syntax while we keep the
语义是一样的, 我们可能会发现, 这里有一些语法
semantics the same and we might discover. That there, that some kinds of syntax are
对于我们感兴趣的问题, 对于语言来说, 比其他的更好
better than others for the problems that we're interested in, for the languages
我们感兴趣的是, 分离两者的另一个原因是
that we're interested in. And another reason for separating the two is because
因为语法和语义不是一对一的
of expressions and meanings because syntax and semantics are not in one to one
我用正则表达式来说明这一点
correspondents. And I actually illustrated this with regular expressions in the
之前的视频, 但我想在这里进行迭代, 这里有更多的内容
previous video but I want to iterate here that, that there are generally many more
表达式比有意义所以这意味着可能有多种方法
expressions than there are meanings so that means there maybe multiple way. To
写一个表示相同的表达式, 我想花点时间
write an expression that means the same thing. I'd like to take a moment to
说明为什么将语法和语义分开是对符号有益的。
illustrate why separating syntax from semantics is beneficial for a notation.
每个人都熟悉r数字系统所以我可以写一些数字
So, everybody's familiar with the, the r number system so I can write numbers like
0 1 42和107有很好的算法来描述你如何添加
zero, one. 42 and 107 and there are very nice algorithms for describing how you add
然后减去并乘以这些数字但是有一些更古老的符号系统
and subtract and multiply such numbers but there are older systems of notation for
数字, 像罗马数字, 我可以有数字1, 我可以
numbers. Things like the Roman numerals. I could have the number one. I could have
数字4, 数字10, 我认为数字40是这样写的
the number four, the number ten and say the number 40 I think is written like that
关于这个数字系统的一个问题, 首先, 我要强调一下这两个
and. And an issue with this number system, first of all, let me stress that these two
有相同的意思, 在这个语言中, 表达式的意义
have the same meaning. So the, the meanings of expressions in this language
这些是整数, 在这个语言中是完全一样的, 所以这个概念,
are. Are the integers and it's exactly the same in this language. So the idea, the
这两个系统的均值是数字但符号是非常的
mean ing of these two systems are just the numbers but the notation is extremely
不同的, 用罗马数字写的数字与a完全不同
different. The number written in Roman numerals was completely different from a
用阿拉伯数字写的数字, 事实是罗马数字是真的
number written in Arabic numerals. And the fact is that the Roman numerals are really
痛苦地做加法, 减法, 乘法, 事实上, 回到
painfully to do addition and subtraction and multiplication and in fact. Back in
在古代, 这是一个共同的系统并不是很清楚如何去做
ancient times when this was a common system was not very well known how to do
只有很少的人能熟练地进行算术运算
it and very few people were actually good at doing arithmetic with, with the system
因为, 因为算法有点复杂, 当我们移动到
because of, because the algorithms were kind of complicated. And, when we moved to
后来, 阿拉伯语系统, 这是一个很大的进步因为人们, 它是
the, the Arabic system, later, That it was a big improvement because people, it was
人们更容易学习如何用这些数字来做基本的算术运算。
easier for people to learn how to do basic arithmetic with these kinds of numbers.
在一个系统和另一个系统之间唯一改变的是
And the only thing that changed between one system and the other was the system of
符号, 所以, 符号是非常重要的因为它决定了你的思维方式
notation. And so, notation is extremely important because it governs how you think
它支配着你能说的事情以及你的程序
and it governs the kinds of things you can say and the sort of procedures that you
使用, 所以不要低估了符号的重要性这是一个
will use. So don't underestimate the importance of notation and this is one
将语法与语义分离的原因, 因为我们可以忽略
reason for separating syntax from semantics because we can leave the idea of
我们要做的不仅仅是数字, 而是用不同的方式来玩
what we're trying to do than numbers alone. And play with, with different ways
代表他们, 我们可能会发现有些方法比其他方法更好。
of representing them and we might discover that some ways are better than others. The
我给出分离语法和语义的第三个原因是在很多有趣的方面
third reason I gave for separating syntax and semantics is that in many interesting
语言、多个表达式、多个语法都是相同的
languages, multiple expressions, multiple pieces of syntax will have the same
语义, 现在回到正则表达式, 让我们考虑一下正则表达式
semantics. Now going back again to regular expressions, let's consider the regular
现在有很多方法来写同样的语言, 也就是
expression zerolt;i>. Now there are many ways to write the same language which is thelt;/i>
所有字符串的语言, 所有长度的0串, 所以
language of all strings of zeroes so string of zeroes of any length. So for
我也可以把它写成0+0, 另一种写法是
example I could also write that as zero + zerolt;i>. Another way to write it is aslt;/i>
0和0, 这里你可以看到, 这个表达式都是
epsilon + zero, zero and here you can see that, that this expression is all the
0的字符串至少链接1然后我们得到了epsilon的空字符串
strings of 0s of at least link one and then we get the empty string for epsilon
所以这是零, 然后, 你知道吗, 这些东西的任何组合
so that is = zero and then just, you know? Any combination of these things
也可以是一个eq的ui价语言, 例如一个, 等等。
would also amount to an eq uivalent language for example that one and so on.
所以实际上有一个无限的, 无限的方式我可以这样写
So there's actually an unbounded, unlimited number of way I could write this
语言, 但所有这些都是完全一样的如果你思考一下, 什么
language but all of these mean exactly the same thing and if you think about it. What
这意味着, 一般来说, 如果我用不同的方式画出这两个域, 我想
this means is that in general, if I draw the two domains differently, I think about
这里有不同的表达式这里有不同的含义
different expressions over here and different distinct meanings over here and
在它们之间映射的函数L, L的函数L很多, 所以有。
the function L that maps between them. The function L is many to one. So there are.
是的, 在这个空间里有很多不同的表达或片段
Yeah. There are points in the space that where many different expressions or pieces
语法映射到相同的意思, 这只是一个一般的特征
of syntax map to the same meaning. And this is just a general characteristic of
有趣的正式语言这在编译器中是非常重要的
Interesting formal languages and this is actually extremely important in compilers
因为这是优化的基础, 事实上有很多不同之处
because this is the basis of optimization. The fact that there are many different
这些程序在功能上是等同的, 这让我们可以
programs that are actually functionally equivalent, that's what allows us to
用一个比另一个更快的程序来代替, 这就是我们要做的
substitute one program that runs faster than another, that's what allows us to
如果一个程序运行得更快, 并且做的完全相同, 那么就替换一个程序
replace one program with another if it runs faster and does exactly the same
所以我们不能进行优化, 你知道我们可以做优化的原因
thing. So we couldn't do optimization and, you know the reason we can do optimization
确切地说, 因为意义函数是很多的, 所以意义是很多的
as precisely because the meaning function is many to one. So meaning is many to one
记住, 重要的一点是, 它从来都不是很多, 我们不想要
and keep in mind, important point here it's never one to many. We don't want the
相反的情况, 如果我们有相反的情况, L可以映射a
opposite situation. If we have the opposite situation, Where L could map a
单点到两种不同的意思, 首先, 这将不再是
single point to two different meanings. Well first of all, this would no longer be
一个函数, 但它也意味着某些表达式的含义
a function but, but also it would mean that the meaning of certain expressions
在我们的编程语言中没有很好的定义, 那就是当你写a的时候
say in our programming language was not well defined. That's that when you wrote a
程序实际上是模糊的不管它是指这个还是它的意思, 这是a
program was actually ambiguous whether it meant this or it meant that and that's a
我们不喜欢的情况, 所以, 我们期望意义函数是很多的
situation we don't like. So, we expect meaning functions to be many to one for
非平凡的语言, 我们不希望它们成为太多的语言, 而且
nontrivial languages and we don't want them ever to be one too many. And that
今天的视频结束了, 下一次, 我们将继续, 继续
concludes today's video. Next time, Going to go back and continue with our
讨论词汇分析。
discussion of lexical analysis.